When it comes to selling homegoods, IKEA
breaks some important rules. Most
simply, at base, IKEA isn't that
convenient. Just take someone living in
the Commonwealth Park neighborhood in
Charlotte, North Carolina, looking to
buy a dresser. There's a Rooms to Go and
K&D's discount store just down the road.
There are a couple of Ashley Home
Furniture and Ashley outlets in the
surrounding area. And then there's the
single IKEA location in the city, not to
mention the state. in fact is the only
IKEA store in a 230 m or 370 km radius.
And should they choose to make this
drive, upon arrival, there's competition
all around. There's an Ashley's, a Bob's
Discount Furniture, a furniture row, and
a furniture market warehouse in the
direct vicinity of this IKEA. Of all of
these options, it's a safe bet that the
shopping experience, parking, finding
the dressers on the showroom floor, and
making a final selection will take the
longest at IKEA. The showroom is
designed as a maze. The store is
absolutely massive. The names of the
dressers are all in Swedish, and should
one purchase the dresser, it'll be on
them to assemble it once they get the
box home. And yet, in spite of all the
inconveniences, in spite of all the far
easier to navigate alternatives, there's
a good chance they opt for IKEA, and
there's a good chance they enjoy the
experience, too. It's a pretty common
outcome. IKEA wins in the US, even if
it's at an extreme numerical
disadvantage, because not only is IKEA
inconvenient, its stores are extremely
few and far between. These are all the
Ashley Home furniture locations in
Texas. As America's top furniture
manufacturer, there are 64 locations
within just the state. IKEA, by
contrast, has just 10 stores in Texas
and 60 in the entire US. Given this
discrepancy, it'd be fair to assume that
perhaps IKEA is recognizable because of
its cult following, or because of its
Swedish meatball forward food court, or
because you've been there a time or two
and have managed to get hopelessly lost
in labyrinth themed showrooms, all
making it feel a more significant player
in the furniture sector than it actually
is. But such an assumption would be
wrong. IKEA does numbers. While the US
furniture market is heavily fragmented
and while exact rankings are hard to
come by, IKEA is one of the largest
furniture companies in the US. Reporting
5.5 billion in total sales for the
fiscal year of 2024, aided by the sale
of some 62 million meat and veggie balls
in their cafes, IKEA US, with just a
fraction of the stores, is generally
understood as a top furniture seller in
the nation. What's more impressive about
the scale of IKEA's empire is that the
US isn't even IKEA's largest market.
There are as many stores and more sales
in Germany. As the logo, the branding,
and the Swedish and Swedish meatballs
help convey, IKEA is proud of its
Swedish origin. Its style and strategy
is heavily Scandinavian. But today, it's
undeniably a global company. While it
still maintains a managerial footprint
within Sweden, its parent company, Enko
Holdings, and the branch that controls
franchising is headquartered in the
Netherlands. As for manufacturing, much
of this happens in Poland with its
wooden products manufactured by IKEA
industry. In 2025, IKEA opened its first
location in New Zealand, an
appropriately isolated country to mark a
pretty unprecedented 64th total country
served. With the likes of Walmart and
Costco yet to break into the 20s in
countries served, it's only Ashley Home
Stores that have a similarly global
reach. In just this decade, IKEA has
opened in as diverse and distinct of
locations as Macau and Estonia, Slovenia
and Chile, the Philippines, and Mexico.
All this has pushed IKEA into the top 10
most valuable retail companies in the
world. In an industry where the products
are big and heavy and the sales are
informed by culture and taste, IKEA has
managed to succeed truly worldwide. How
IKEA's gotten to this point, how IKEA
makes this all work can best be
explained by this bookshelf. The Billy
bookcase has been around since the
1970s. Its design is as radically simple
as its intended purpose to actually
shelf books, and it's likely you've seen
one of these before. The Billy blends
into just about every environment. And
because it's so neutral, it's equally
likely you don't remember seeing one
before. It's also endlessly
customizable, or as IKEA enthusiasts and
DIYers would call it, hackable. This is
a Billy, and this is also a Billy. And
the Billy sells like crazy. In 2023,
IKEA had sold some 140 million of the
shelving units. In other words, there's
about one Billy bookcase for every 60
people on Earth. an outstanding level of
adoption for a household product on a
global scale. Such absurd levels of
popularity weren't likely forecasted
when the product launched, but the
product's success can be tied to
adherence to the IKEA design guidelines.
The company calls it democratic design,
and every product it sells has to fill
much of this chart. When Ingvar Comprad
opened the first IKEA in 1958, the idea
was to sell products that bettered
everyday life for everyday people. The
concept matured into these foundational
pillars. Each product needs to do its
job. It needs to look good. It needs to
last. It needs to use material
efficiently, and it needs to be sold at
a reasonable price for the everyday
consumer. The Billy is really good at
its job, storing far more than just
books. It's light on materials. Its
design is neutral, and it can be left
neutral for a clean, minimalist
Scandinavian look, or dressed up and
adorned. And many owners say their
bookcases have held up well under years
of weight and moves from one place to
another. But most of all, the Billy is
cheap. In the US, the standard 80 cm
wide unit sits right at $100. A number
that's not throwaway money, but a price
that seems a real bargain when
considering the build quality is high
enough for it to confidently last a
decade. It's this blend of values that's
made the Billy into a global star and
the ability to blend multiple positive
traits together that's made IKEA a
global star. IKEA has approached
expansion with a combination of national
and regional pride along with pragmatism
and cultural understanding. At first,
IKEA's expansion outside of Sweden
stayed in Scandinavia, launching in
Norway and Denmark in the60s. In the
70s, it went farther abroad, launching
stores in western or westernized
countries as nearby as West Germany and
as far away as Canada and Australia. And
in the 70s, there was a hiccup. While
IKEA planners saw continuity in
minimalist wood forward Scandinavian
design with popular tastes in Japan,
subtle cultural differences proved
IKEA's first expansion into Asia tricky.
The company tried to ameliorate. Rather
than open a massive warehouse store,
IKEA franchise holders in Japan opened a
series of IKEA corner shops in larger
department stores. And according to
reviewers, the design taste of 1970s
IKEA fit Japanese culture well. But
products just didn't sell. Even when the
company launched a full-size warehouse
in 1981, sales lacked. The failure was
due to functionality. While products
looked the part, they were just too big
and bulky for the typical Japanese
apartment. They didn't fold up in the
corner or serve multiple purposes. And
while they were packaged as efficiently
as possible, they were just too hard to
transport from shop to home without a
car. Making matters worse, while IKEA
had fully leaned into DIY assembly to
keep costs down, Japanese culture puts
real value in services and found the
fact that the consumer had to assemble
the piece to be a turnoff. IKEA and
Japan didn't take, but the company
learned lessons in products, design, and
services. If it were to go global, it
had to be more flexible. When IKEA
launched in the US, the company saw an
odd spike in flower vase sales and
adjusted accordingly. Americans saw
minimal use for Scandinavian glass drink
wear because it was so small and had
unintentionally begun to buy the flower
vases as glasses. So, IKEA went bigger.
More recently, as the company has
expanded into China and India, it's
taken steps to ameliate its products
with these markets. In China, this has
looked like adding products and design
ideas for balcony spaces, a commonality
in Chinese homes that are far less
prevalent in the West. In India, they
have minimized the use of untreated pine
and added rubber footings to much of
their wooden offerings, as it's just too
humid for pine to last, and it's custom
to wash floors with water, which would
damage products without the rubber
footings. To better serve Indian
cultures tendency for large family
gatherings at home, IKEA has also
created easily expandable tables and
collapsible chairs for their Indian
stores. Subtle but thoughtful product
development ensures functionality of
Swedish design in different loces. This
goes beyond products, too. While IKEA's
product names are Swedish, they're
screened before entering a new market to
ensure they don't overlap with anything
vulgar or unbecoming in the local
language. The same goes with the
cafeteria. There will certainly be the
staples like Swedish meatballs, but
there are also going to be local dishes,
too. Where function differs from culture
to culture, IKEA is willing to adapt.
This adaptability extends to pricing
products, too. If you were in the market
for a fairly mid-priced bed frame, you
may settle on this, the $249 momm
queen-sized bed frame. With full head
and footboards and thick side rails, the
frame is sleek in design, but not
exactly small. And yet, if you're headed
to pick it up from the store, you
wouldn't have to worry about it fitting
in the car, as the two boxes it comes
in, with a little creative rearranging,
can fit into a midsized sedan. The two
boxes will be heavy, but they'll take up
the tiniest amount of space possible
because IKEA is really good at not
shipping air. Since the company's
founding, it saved money through flat
packing, a simple concept that saves the
company more and more money at scale. By
sending its products with assembly
instructions rather than assembled, IKEA
is able to stuff a chest of drawers into
a box the tenth of the size, then able
to send 10 such products in the space of
one fully assembled. While it didn't
invent the concept, it popularized it.
It designed products to further optimize
for it, and it built its logistics
around it. Space savings opens up an
entirely new pathway for IKEA products.
The materials for a mom bed frame bound
to be sold in the US don't necessarily
have to be sourced or manufactured in
the US. They can still come from the
cheaper labor and material markets of
Poland, then get shipped in
hyperefficient packaging over to the
American market. The benefits of the
flat packing model go further, too. Now
IKEA is able to store products in store
because they just don't take up a ton of
space. They can save on labor because
the expectation is on the consumer to
build out the product and not them. And
they don't have to employ a delivery
service because the consumer can come to
the box store and expect that just about
anything they buy can fit into the back
of their car or truck. All these savings
then allow for the company to keep
prices down to keep the mom at $249.
But the effort to keep prices down goes
further. In 2008, the IKEA catalog had
the mom listed at $179.
In 2012, the price had actually dropped
to $149,
$50 cheaper than the year prior. Fast
forward to today, and the product is
still in the same relative price range.
And when accounting for inflation, it's
actually cheaper to buy the bed frame
today than it was in 2008. That's
because the product has changed. The MOM
has always been made out of composite
wood rather than solid wood, which makes
room for the company to use leftover and
recycled material rather than harvested
timber to further costsaving and
sustainability efforts. But even today,
compared to 2012 and 2008 models, the
Mal is lighter on materials than ever,
as the head and footboards aren't even
solid particle board, but filled with a
honeycomb cardboard structure to
maintain rigidity, but save on materials
and weight. It's a compromise on quality
and sturdiness, and customers notice.
And this much is a reflection of the
industry changing beyond IKEA's control.
In 2024 and 2025, IKEA marked
backto-back years of slightly depressed
sales. Years where they actually sold
more product, but at lower rates after
the company employed a price cutting
campaign across all its markets. It was
a response to the realities of being a
furniture brand. When the economy slows,
when home sales are down, there's just
less natural demand for large item
furniture. And there's also the
competition. When IKEA only counts on
online sales for about a quarter of its
business and would far rather have you
visit, the low price furniture
competition only gets more fierce as
Wayfair and Walmart expand into the
space. American tariffs compound
difficulties, too. And while they're
less steep than those facing competitors
importing from China, it's another
challenge they assert little control
over. But mitigating market uncertainty
is IKEA's ability to control the
experience of shopping at IKEA. Much has
been made over the years about how IKEA
store layouts and products subtly
manipulate the customer. They have terms
for it. There's the Gruin effect, how
IKEA uses an immersive shopping
experience to force interaction with
more products and cause more spontaneous
buying. There's the Ditto effect, the
perceived need to buy matching sets,
turning a single purchase into multiple
purchases. There's even the IKEA effect
where a consumer has a higher perceived
value of a product that they had a hand
in constructing or in the case of IKEA
assembling. But there's also a more
basic underlying explanation as to why
IKEA is able to sell so much out of so
few locations. Visiting an IKEA is just
a fairly fun and highly standardized
experience. Since the 1980s, every IKEA
has come with a modern, spacious cafe.
Every IKEA has been serving coffee,
local favorites, and Swedish staples,
most importantly and iconically, Swedish
meatballs with mashed potatoes and
lingberry. The timing was no accident.
With typical furniture business slowed
by the 1979 oil crisis, IKEA had to
scheme up new ways to boost revenue.
They had experience in cafes across the
locations. They had the space, so they
piloted a larger, more modern cafe with
a Swedish forward menu. The concept was
a major hit. Today, food sales account
for about 6% of the company's revenues.
Nearly a third of all customers site the
cafe as a reason for them visiting. And
IKEA is now a top 10 food seller outside
the US. But numbers only begin to
explain the impact of the cafe on the
larger business location. Because IKEA
locations are usually on the periphery
of urban areas where land for such
massive warehouses is going to be
cheaper, IKEA will always be a
destination. The cafe helps make the
destination appealing. What may start
out as a weekend chore, like buying a
new dresser, now can be reframed as an
outing. Drive all the way out to IKEA,
peruse the dresser options, grab a
decent lunch at a decent price, then
make a final decision on the dresser.
Now, with a built-in lunch spot, a
rushed visit becomes more leisurely, and
a box store stop that would normally be
like pulling teeth for a family outing
actually becomes palatable for kids and
parents alike. What was a chore is now
an experience. is an experience that
they lean into further throughout the
showrooms. IKEA actively wants customers
to sit on the sofa and sprawl out over
the display mattresses. They want you to
feel the fabrics as you meander through
the space and envision yourself and your
home when walking through their room
layouts. IKEA wants your money, but in a
world where transactions feel rushed and
murky, goods can feel cheap and scammy,
IKEA goes about getting your money in
what feels like the opposite manner.
From its product design to its
storefronts, everything IKEA does is
aimed to blend a sense of comforting
approachability with a flare of
intriguing foreignness. You're not
expected to know how to pronounce the
product names. You're not supposed to
have an exact sense as to where you are
in the store once you've entered the
showroom, but you know you can count on
fairly cheap, fairly reliable products
and a shopping experience that's going
to be exactly that, an experience.
Similar to Costco and Trader Joe's, IKEA
exists in a unique space with a consumer
where most have come to by and large
trust the product and enjoy the
experience. IKEA is by no means perfect
from problematic politics of its founder
to illegally sourced materials and
horsemeat scandals. The company
certainly has blemishes on its record,
but the company has addressed its
missteps, moved forward, and kept
providing what feels like decent
products at honest prices in a manner
that maximizes the experience of what's
usually objectively not fun. In a world
that's increasingly fast, convenient,
and online, IKEA has gone the other
direction and stuck to a formula it
figured out in the 70s, which is exactly
why people love it.
Going against the trends of an
increasingly fast, convenient, and
well-connected world is also the theme
of a series I've come to love. This
summer, Downey Express debuted its third
season, documenting Michael Downey and
his friend Sebastian's journey from
Bangkok to Bali by way of trains and
fairies. Across the four 40 plus minute
professionally produced and genuinely
excellent episodes, Michael and
Sebastian pass through some amazing
landscapes, navigate some public
transportation systems that Western
tourists rarely interact with, and
explore some fascinating cultures and
places from ground level. Along with
their banter and occasional travel
missteps, it's really all you can ask
for from a travel show. And this is
coming from a person that makes a travel
show. I highly recommend that you check
out this season of Downey Express, and I
highly recommend checking out the
service that makes it. and so many other
cool shows possible. Nebula shows like
Downey Express or our own travel game
show, Jetlack the Game, just wouldn't
exist without Nebula. Nebula is a
streaming service that allows creators
like myself, Michael Downey, Tom Scott,
Lindsay Ellis, and so many more to take
on projects with bigger scopes, more
creative and risky angles, and bigger
budgets. For shows like Downey Express,
and Jetlag, if you want to get access to
them earlier, and if you want to watch
them without ads, you can do so on
Nebula. For larger projects like our
documentary series called Scav following
America's biggest annual scavenger hunt
or Jason from Not just Bikes series
exploring and profiling European public
transport systems called Day pass. You
can only access these shows through
Nebula. Nebula is owned by creators and
made for creators. And for years now
we've been adding to the catalog and
really investing in the product. It's a
streaming service that posts our stuff
first and without ads. It houses some of
our biggest and most original products.
and it goes a long way in supporting us
through sponsor spots like this. It's a
product we're confident in and it's a
product that's priced at what we believe
is a really approachable number. If you
want to give it a try and support this
channel and some of your favorite
creators, follow my link and get 50% off
Nebula. That makes it just $30 a year or
$25 a month at nebula.tv/wendover.